<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Geekstuff | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/categories/geekstuff/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cvquesty.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-13T23:40:16-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://cvquesty.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PuppetConf 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/09/23/puppetconf-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T13:19:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/09/23/puppetconf-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Glad to be at PuppetConf with #ShadowSoft exploring all the latest and greatest in PuppetLabs.</p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/puppetconf.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southeast Puppet User's Group September]]></title>
    <link href="http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/southeast-puppet-users-group-september/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T18:33:01-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/southeast-puppet-users-group-september</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/puppet_docker.jpg" alt="image" /></p>

<p>John Ray is bringing the Puppet + Docker goodness in his talk tonight: &ldquo;Deploying Docker Containers with Puppet&rdquo;.  Join us each month at the Shadow Soft offices for the latest in DEVOPS topics and information.  Always fun, lots of discussion and information surrounding Puppet topics and associated technologies.  There&rsquo;s always pizza and beverages of all kinds, and we&rsquo;ve finally moved into our new meeting/class rooms, so come on out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Toolbox Grows...]]></title>
    <link href="http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/toolbox-grows/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T11:57:18-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/toolbox-grows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So far we&rsquo;ve gotten our heads around some important things.  First and foremost, vim.  Our editor and companion for creating great code and ways to see our code in action and be able to determine at a glance whether our syntax is correct.  Also, we&rsquo;ve looked at revision control.  The single largest &ldquo;CYA&rdquo; ohmygodimgladivegotanoldercopytorestoreto sort of paradigm where you can roll yourself back to previously &ldquo;known good&rdquo; revisions to save that day&hellip;besides that, it&rsquo;s just darned good practice to keep your code externally saved, revision controlled, and accessible.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also talked about importance of workflow clarity and quality.  If you implement a poor workflow, you just have an automated <em>poor </em>workflow. Key word here is &ldquo;poor&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Next up on our browse through the &ldquo;toolbox&rdquo; is &ldquo;Vagrant&rdquo;.  What is this Vagrant, you ask?</p>

<p>Virtualization is paramount in today&rsquo;s world in a number of ways and for a number of reasons.  For extending your server farms to handle even more application expression, to expand your own desktop machines to test/try different operating systems, and even just rolling up an ad-hoc VM so you can try something without touching a &ldquo;real&rdquo; machine in your environment.</p>

<p>Some may disagree, but I&rsquo;ve found virtualization to be one of the most powerful tools added to the toolbox in years.  Not only can you prototype systems or applications, but you can prototype entire environments.  This is where Vagrant shines, and especially in the context of Puppet (master + clients), allows you to create a fully functioning Puppet environment upon which to develop, prototype, and test without ever jeopardizing even the least important system of your infrastructure.  I count that as a &ldquo;win&rdquo;.  Let&rsquo;s see what this tool can do.</p>

<p><em><strong>What <em>is</em> Vagrant?</strong></em></p>

<p>According to its website:</p>

<p>Vagrant provides easy to configure, reproducible, and portable work environments built on top of industry-standard technology and controlled by a single consistent workflow to help maximize the productivity and flexibility of you and your team.</p>

<p>To achieve its magic, Vagrant stands on the shoulders of giants. Machines are provisioned on top of VirtualBox, VMware, AWS, or any other provider. Then, industry-standard provisioning tools such as shell scripts, Chef, or Puppet, can be used to automatically install and configure software on the machine.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot there, but it&rsquo;s just a fancy way of saying exactly what I said before.  Vagrant is essentially a framework system that wraps your virtualization engine to manage <em>environments </em>of VMs.  Here is where Vagrant will hold the power for us.</p>

<p><em><strong>Virtualization</strong></em></p>

<p>If Vagrant is the framework, then Virtualization is the foundation.  Now, I&rsquo;ve chosen to use &ldquo;Virtualbox&rdquo; for my virtualization technology, but VMWare works every bit as well.  I am doing all my testing over Virtualbox, however, so YMMV.  Virtualbox is freely available from oracle, and you can download the appropriate version from Virtualbox at <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org.">https://www.virtualbox.org.</a>  I am running the latest version at 4.3.12 (as of this writing) and it serves the Vagrant system extremely well.</p>

<p><em><strong>Vagrant</strong></em></p>

<p>Next, you&rsquo;ll need to install Vagrant on your system.  You can find all the right packages at <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com.">http://www.vagrantup.com.</a>  I am currently running version 1.6.3 without errors.</p>

<p>[warning]I want to make a disclaimer here since I&rsquo;ve had an issue or two with Vagrant on a platform I don&rsquo;t use-Windows.  I am a Mac &amp; Linux user, and have had no issues using the Vagrant/Virtualbox combo on either of these.  However, literally every time I&rsquo;ve used Vagrant over Windows, it&rsquo;s just been a mess.  I&rsquo;ve known one person (ONE!) who has gotten Vagrant to work over Windows, and it required his getting into the product, editing code, etc.  As such, I wouldn&rsquo;t recommend it for those new to the platform.[/warning]</p>

<p>On the Mac platform, you get a .dmg file and can extract it run the installer.  Linux versions are available as RPM installs and Debian Packages.  Once you&rsquo;re installed, let&rsquo;s mess around a bit with Vagrant to see what we can do.</p>

<p><em><strong>Getting Started</strong></em></p>

<p>Vagrant is a unique tool in that it allows you to manage all these varied VMs, but adds a twist.  The big twist is that you don&rsquo;t have to have the <em>source </em>materials for the VMs you&rsquo;re installing.  In fact, the simplicity of turning up a new VM is astounding.  Take the following series of commands:</p>

<p>cd <your favorite directory>
mkdir precise32
cd precise32
vagrant init hashicorp/precise32
vagrant up</p>

<p>If your Vagrant is installed correctly, a number of things start to happen.  First, Vagrant places a file in your cwd called &ldquo;Vagrantfile&rdquo;.  Your vagrant file (indie) looks like this:</p>

<p>[snippet id=&ldquo;34&rdquo;]</p>

<p>Note that this is a long file with a lot of explanatory documentation.  In actuality, the most important part of your Vagrantfile can be summed up here:</p>

<p>[snippet id=&ldquo;35&rdquo;]</p>

<p>These are the lines that are uncommented plus the top two declaratives that tell Vagrant what to do.  It&rsquo;s a very simple file that does some very powerful things.  First, it checks your home directory in the ~/.vagrant.d location to see if you already have the &ldquo;precise32&rdquo; Vagrant source &ldquo;box&rdquo;.  (more on boxes later).  Next, if you do have this, it will simply start up a VM in your virtualization of choice with a randomized name.  For instance, mine is called &ldquo;precise32_default_1402504453444_30545&rdquo;.  Vagrant takes away the selection of an .iso image, connecting it to the virtual CD/DVD Rom, starting an installer, etc.  It simply sends you a pre-rolled image, places it in your .vagrant.d directory, and provisions the VM to respond to Vagrant commands, and starts it up within Virtualbox.  Precise32 is simply a test scenario, as Vagrant&rsquo;s site has quite a number of varied and specially configured &ldquo;box&rdquo; files that you can use to prototype on at their &ldquo;ready-made&rdquo; box discovery site: <a href="https://vagrantcloud.com/discover/featured.">https://vagrantcloud.com/discover/featured.</a>  You can install boxes with too many variations and differentiations to enumerate here, and that&rsquo;s not really the point for our purposes&hellip; you may find these of great assistance in your own workplace, but let&rsquo;s continue.</p>

<p>When you run your &ldquo;vagrant init&rdquo; command listed above, it places a Vagrantfile, and when you do a &ldquo;vagrant up&rdquo;, it automatically retrieves your box file, provisions, and starts the VM.  Now, by simply running &ldquo;vagrant ssh default&rdquo;, you are now logged into this virtual machine!  You also have full sudo to become root and do any sort of damage you may wish to do.  If you logout (&ldquo;exit&rdquo; or CTRL-D), and type &ldquo;vagrant destroy&rdquo;, the VM goes away and you have nothing in Virtualbox.</p>

<p>Were we to just stop here, the power inherent in being able to just have these &ldquo;Vagrantfiles&rdquo; (sort of like a &ldquo;Makefile&rdquo; for boxes) to spin up and down test scenarios at will is incredible.  But, let&rsquo;s look at this in light of the Vagrantfile, what it can do and how you can customize it.  There is an entire descriptive language surrounding Vagrant PLUS Vagrant has a plugin infrastructure whereby developers can extend Vagrant&rsquo;s capabilities.  We will capitalize on these later.</p>

<p>So, imagine a scenario where you can create a directory, copy a text file into it, run a single command, and it automatically provisions a 4-node Puppet Enterprise infrastructure, fully installed with a master and three agents, MCollective fully installed, PuppetDB installed and in use&hellip;  literally a full installation just like you would use for your infrastructure&hellip;  Now we get powerful.  NOW we have the ability to do some cool things.</p>

<p>Next time, that&rsquo;s exactly what we&rsquo;re going to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Puppet User's Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/puppet-users-group/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T18:59:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/puppet-users-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Going on right now at Shadow Soft!</p>

<p><a href="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/pug_robert.jpg"><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/pug_robert.jpg" alt="20140508-195822.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>Excellent coverage of AWS automation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/vim/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-02T14:56:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cvquesty.github.io/blog/2014/05/02/vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Old School</strong></p>

<p>Why on earth am I starting with Vim?  (or &ldquo;vi&rdquo; for you old folks)</p>

<p>Vim is the modern &ldquo;vi&rdquo; implementation.  A full-screen text editor with a myriad of options and abilities for beyond anything I could ever cover here.  But Vim has one thing going for it that no other text editor has.  One simple fact about it puts it in the category of cameras.  You know the old saying?</p>

<p><em><strong>&ldquo;The best camera is the one you have with you.&rdquo;</strong></em></p>

<p>Thus it is with vi/vim.  It&rsquo;s literally <strong>everywhere.</strong></p>

<p>Every UNIX OS, commercial or not, streamlined or not, old or new, has vi or vim installed on it.  Emacs is a great product, but it just isn&rsquo;t installed by default everywhere.  Regardless of the editor you refer to, ${INSERT_EDITOR_HERE} just isn&rsquo;t as ubiquitous as Vi/Vim.</p>

<p>Since we&rsquo;re talking about a modern pursuit and workflow (DEVOPS), we&rsquo;ll be talking mostly about Vim&rsquo;s capabilities and features.</p>

<p><strong>What Vim is <em>NOT</em></strong></p>

<p>Vim is not a word processor.  You won&rsquo;t be writing business letters with it.  Vim is not for writing resumes, making pretty newsletters, or for typesetting a magazine.  The die-hard Vi/Vim fan will tell you that you can do all of the above with it, but that falls into the same category as filling in the Grand Canyon with a teaspoon. You <em>can </em>do it, but why on earth would you want to?</p>

<p><strong>What Vim Does Best</strong></p>

<p>Vim edits text.  Plain&hellip;text.  Not pretty bold, italicized, with all sorts of alignment characters and strange paragraphs and pagination doohickeys&hellip; no, Vim just makes text files.  Text files that are SO devoid of bells and whistles, in fact, that when you open a Vim created file in your favorite WYSIWYG editor, you&rsquo;ll see what appears to be a pile of letters and such all crammed together like you had nothing else on your keyboard but letters, numbers, and punctuation.</p>

<p>Vim allows you to eliminate all the cruft and get right down to the matter of creating plain, unencumbered text files.</p>

<p><strong>Why Does it Matter?</strong></p>

<p>When you&rsquo;re logged onto your favorite Linux through two bastion hosts across several continents and have latency to boot, WordPad will not help.  You&rsquo;ll need a lightweight text editor within which you can load, edit, and save the single most numerous type of item on a UNIX system&hellip; a text file.</p>

<p><strong>Where Can I learn More About Vim?</strong></p>

<p>Vim&rsquo;s main project page can be found <a href="http://www.vim.org">here</a> online.  The main page has links to documentation and various community links as well as connections to various types of plugins and add ons you can use with Vim for any number of tasks.  You can join online forums, mailing lists, and communities whose entire purpose is the extension and promotion of Vim.  But that&rsquo;s not what we&rsquo;re up to&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>How We Will Use Vim</strong></p>

<p>For our purposes, we will use vim as code editor.  No more, no less.  Vim&rsquo;s abilities can help us <em>see </em>our code in ways that let&rsquo;s us know when there&rsquo;s an issue and can direct us generally in the direction of our solutions.  So, let&rsquo;s dive in to a minor Vim tutorial.  (If you&rsquo;re an advanced Vim user, stick with me&hellip;)</p>

<p>All Linux distributions and Mac OSX come with Vim pre-installed and ready for action.  Note that some distributions of Linux will have <em>both </em>Vim and Vi.  You will either need to get into the habit of running &ldquo;vim&rdquo; from the command line, or setup your shell aliases to load Vim every time you type &ldquo;vi&rdquo; instead.</p>

<p>When you launch Vim, you see a screen much like the following.  I use Mac OSX, but the effect is the same, regardless of platform.</p>

<p><a href="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/vim.png"><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/vim.png" alt="vim_screen" /></a></p>

<p>I have several features turned on (including the line across the bottom that provides me a lot of information about the file I&rsquo;m editing), but the main things we will talk about here are <em>syntax highlighting</em> and <em>plugins </em>after a short tutorial on how Vim works.</p>

<p><strong>I Can&rsquo;t DO Anything!!!</strong></p>

<p>Most people&rsquo;s frustrations begin right on this page.  From here, nothing seems familiar.  I can&rsquo;t pull down a menu and I can&rsquo;t really even choose &ldquo;exit&rdquo; from a list of things to do.  The only real hint I have is on the screen above:</p>

<p>type  :q<Enter>               to exit</p>

<p>&hellip;which is quite a peculiar directive.  Why do I have to type a colon?  What does it mean?  And goodness help you if you already managed to type something into the screen.  The instructions you see above disappear, and without the right collection of keystrokes, you&rsquo;re not getting out of Vim.  You&rsquo;ll most likely just close the window and start looking for &ldquo;notepad&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s where the tutorial starts.</p>

<p>Vim is what is known as a full-screen text editor.  It started back in the Amiga days, and was first released publicly in 1991.  Before Vi/Vim, to create text files, there were line-based text editors that only allowed you to see one line of a file at a time.  So, you really couldn&rsquo;t work with huge files&hellip;it would be difficult to see file lines compared to each other or look at the whole flow of a subroutine you had written, or even to match wording or syntax from one section to another.</p>

<p>Enter the full-screen editor.</p>

<p>What the full-screen editor did was open a file on disk, reserving space in memory to hold the entire file, and then display to you a &ldquo;window&rdquo; into your file equal to your terminal&rsquo;s display size.  for instance, I have a terminal right now that has a several thousand line file open.  Of that file, I can only see 25 lines and 80 columns wide.  This &ldquo;window&rdquo; onto my file is something I personally configured in my terminal program (in my case, &ldquo;iTerm&rdquo;).  I can scroll up and down this file, sliding forward or backward within the file from the beginning to the end (just as you may an MS Word document) and can interact with/edit any character I can see on the screen.  (we&rsquo;ll talk about search and replace and other such things later).</p>

<p>We are currently in what is known as &ldquo;command mode&rdquo;.  Many would ask why you don&rsquo;t just call this &ldquo;view&rdquo; mode, and the reasons are very simple.  From this screen, you issue MANY commands to Vim and tell it how you want it to behave for you.  For our purposes, we will use &ldquo;command&rdquo; mode and &ldquo;insert&rdquo; mode mostly.</p>

<p><strong>Well, How Do I Edit Something?</strong></p>

<p>To edit your file, you enter into a mode known as &ldquo;insert&rdquo; mode.  From this page there are several different modes you can enter, but &ldquo;insert&rdquo; mode is the easiest.  You simply type a single lowercase &ldquo;i&rdquo; to enter this mode.  When you do so, a cursor appears on the top line of the page you are viewing, and you are now able to type all you like.  Letters, <enter> keys, tabs&hellip; all normal typing idioms are available to you from this point.  How, you may ask, then do you save your work to disk?  I&rsquo;m in this &ldquo;insert&rdquo; mode and don&rsquo;t know how to save!</p>

<p>Think about what you wish to accomplish&hellip; you wish to issue the command &ldquo;save&rdquo; to Vim.  Command&hellip;  as in&hellip; &ldquo;command mode&rdquo;, perhaps?  Well, we have to go back into command mode, then, so we can issue some commands to Vim and exit the program.</p>

<p>Any time you are in Vim, your &ldquo;saving grace&rdquo; is your [esc] key.  Two taps on the escape key lways brings you back to command mode from anywhere.  Go ahead and try it.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll now notice you have returned to &ldquo;command mode&rdquo; just as you were when you first opened Vim.  The only difference is that everything you typed is now on your screen and has not gone away.  Your &ldquo;edit buffer&rdquo; is full of a file you now can do things with.  You can save it, delete it, save it out as a specific file name&hellip; a myriad of normal file operations you may be used to from other software packages.</p>

<p>In our case, we want to just save the file.  However, when we opened Vim, we didn&rsquo;t specify a file name to edit, we just opened Vim.  So, for all intents and purposes, we have an open buffer full of &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; and no file name to associate with it.  What we want to do now is to &ldquo;write&rdquo; the file to disk.  To do so, we have to issue commands to Vim in Command mode.</p>

<p><strong>Command Mode</strong></p>

<p>To issue commands to Vim, we have to tell it we are issuing it a command, otherwise you may hit a letter than means something else.  Recall that simply by hitting a lowercase &ldquo;i&rdquo; we placed vim into insert mode and then by hitting the [esc] key twice, we left it.  Clearly, there&rsquo;s more to this editor than we can readily see, so how do we save the file?</p>

<p>When you have a buffer with text you would like to save, you have to first hit a colon &ldquo;:&rdquo;.  You&rsquo;ll notice that Vim places the colon on the bottom line of your screen to the left, awaiting a command.  While there are several commands we can perform here (as well as joining multiple commands together), we will simply write the file right now.  To do so, while at the &ldquo;colon prompt&rdquo;, we simply type:</p>

<p><strong>: w foo.txt</strong></p>

<p>and press the &ldquo;enter&rdquo; key.  You will receive a message on the last line that lets you know the file has been written to disk:</p>

<p><strong>&ldquo;foo.txt&rdquo; [New] 1L, 16C written</strong></p>

<p>But I&rsquo;m still in Vim.  What do I do now?</p>

<p>Just like &ldquo;w&rdquo; is a command, exiting the program also is a command.  Guessably so, it is the letter &ldquo;q&rdquo; for &ldquo;quit&rdquo;.  So, as before, you hit the colon key, then the letter q, and then the enter key.  If all goes well, you&rsquo;ll be back at the command line.</p>

<p><strong>Much More to This</strong></p>

<p>Were I to do this for all the features of Vim, I&rsquo;d be writing a book.  However, fortunately for you, there are several tutorials and cheat sheets on Vi/Vim all over the Internet.  Here are a few of my favorites.</p>

<p><a href="http://vim.wikia.com/wiki/Tutorial">The Main Vim Tutorial
</a><a href="https://www.linux.com/learn/tutorials/228600-vim-101-a-beginners-guide-to-vim">Linux.com&rsquo;s Vim Tutorial</a></p>

<p>As well as some cheat sheets for you to refer to for quick reference on the various commands available when using Vim:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.viemu.com/vi-vim-cheat-sheet.gif">One of My Favorites
</a><a href="http://vim.rtorr.com">Another Good Cheat Sheet</a></p>

<p>Take some time learning the basics of Vim before pressing on to the next article: &ldquo;Customizing Vim&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
